let's check out an interesting infinite
series you may be familiar with this
infinite series the sum where n ranges
from 0 to Infinity of 1 / n factorial
this infinite sum is famously equal to
the value e consequently this infinite
sum where n ranges from 1 to Infinity of
1 n + 1 factorial must equal eus 2 what
if we modify this series slightly and we
consider the sum where n ranges from 1
to Infinity of n / n +1 factorial this
is the infinite sum 1 over 2 factorial
plus 2 3 factorial plus 3 over 4
factorial and so on what's this infinite
sum this is a series of positive terms
and we can show using a geometric
dissection argument that the partial
sums are bounded above moreover the
dissection argument will show us the
actual sum of the
series let's consider a square whose
side lengths are both one we can cut
this Square in half and shade one of
those halves so that we've shaded one
copy of one2 then we can cut the
remaining half into three equal pieces
each of Area 1 six and shade two of them
so that we've shade 2 * 1 over6 or 2 * 1
3 factorial we can cut the remaining 1
over 3 factorial area into four equal
pieces each of Area 1 24 or 1 4
factorial when we shade three of them
we've shaded 3 * 1 4 factorial now cut
the remaining 1 over4 factorial into
five equal pieces and shade four of them
thus shading 4 * 1 over 5 factorial
repeat this process taking the 1 over 5
factorial that's left cut it into six
equal pieces and shade five of them
shading 5 * 1 over 6 factorial let's do
this again cutting the remaining 1 over
6 factorial into seven equal pieces and
shading six of them for a total of 6 * 1
over 7 factorial we can continue this
process indefinitely each time cutting
the remaining 1 n factorial into n + 1
equal pieces and shading n of them
shading a total area of n / n + 1
factorial at each stage
but now we see that the infinite sum of
interest is the limiting value of the
shaded areas and more importantly we see
that in the limit the entire square area
is shaded therefore the infinite sum
that we're interested in must equal the
area of the square which is 1 * 1 so we
have seen by a geometric dissection that
the sum where n ranges from 1 to
Infinity of n / by n + 1 factorial must
be 1 this is truly amazing that it's
such a simple value given that the two
infinite series that this infinite sum
was related to had values of e and e
minus 2 which are both
irrational